look at this piece of grass hi I'm
Norman and Norman is going to teach you
everything you need to know about how to
write a contextualization paragraph for
your DBQ and your leq more specifically
Norman's going to tell you the two
biggest mistakes students make when
they're writing their contextualization
paragraphs and how to avoid them aren't
you Norman aren't you a he's so cute so
by this point in the year you probably
already know the basic idea of a
contextualization paragraph you have a
thesis and your job is to write about
three sentences is that situates your
thesis in the larger historical context
you know this and yet you keep missing
that point for contextualization so
let's fix that if you listen to to what
Norman and I have to say everything will
be absolutely clear to you and then by
the end of this video I'm going to show
you an easy formula for writing your
contextualization paragraph and we'll
take all the mystery out of it now
according to the rubric you can
contextualize either before during or
after the time period of the prompt but
we'll keep things simple and do our
contextualization before the time period
you're writing about and the general
rule of thumb is that you need to
contextualize with events that occurred
about 50 to 100 years before the time
period you're writing about okay so we
know this now let's go talk to Norman
hey buddy you got a question for us yeah
why am I here a Norman always were an
existential piece of grass and that's
why we love you anyway Let's Help Norman
figure this out I think of all the
different potential ways we could answer
Norman's question I mean we could answer
it scientifically Norman you're here
because your cells convert the light
from the sun into glucose which is
called photosynthesis and that is a
perfectly legitimate answer to his
question but we could also answer his
question politically Norman you're here
on land that I own because the Cherokee
who previously inhabited this patch of
Earth were forcibly removed during the
1830s and now someone of European
descent lives here instead of a Cherokee
family and that's why you are here or
suppose we answer Norman's question
socially Norman you're here because in
the 1950s there was an explosion in
Suburban development one of the key
features of suburbs is landscaped grass
so Norman can you be a little more
specific with your question sure Dad a
he call me dad all right go ahead Norman
evaluate the extent to which I exist
because of the social reorganization
that occurred during the suburbanization
of America all right buddy now that is
something we can work with so here's the
first mistake that many students make in
their contextualization paragraphs if
Norman wants to know why he's here
because of so social realities then my
contextualization paragraph needs to
talk about those social realities that
led to his existence so in this case
here's the mistake that you could easily
make and therefore lose your point your
thesis about Norman's existence is about
social realities but your
contextualization paragraph is not it's
about photosynthesis you know what I
mean like you smell what I'm stepping in
like is it also true that Norman exists
because of photosynthesis yes absolutely
but that's not what the question is
asking so an unrelated contextualization
paragraph even if it says true things
will not earn the point for example if
you have a prompt about how Spanish
colonization affected social realities
in the Americas then you might be
tempted to talk about technology that
enabled the Spanish to go sailing across
the Atlantic you know things like
astrolabes and updated astronomical
charts and new ship designs Etc and did
all those things enable the Spanish to
colonize the Americas yes but it's
unrelated to how their presence in the
Americas affected social realities
instead you need to talk about how
Society was structured in the Americas
before the arrival of the Spanish and
that is a great setup for the argument
you make in your thesis so here's an
example of what I'm talking about do
yourself a favor and pause this and read
them both here's the prompt and then
here's my thesis and then I have a
contextualization paragraph that is
unrelated which earns no points and then
here's one that's related that will
absolutely earn the points now the
second mistake students often make on
their contextualization paragraph is
that they aren't specific enough with
their evidence if you're prompt asks you
about the causes of internal migration
in the United States between 1900 and
1970 then you can't just say before 1900
there was a lot of cultural and social
tension in America I mean yeah that's
true but you have to get specific in
your contextualization like show me what
demonstrates that tension would be the
equivalent of answering Norman's
question about why he's here with you
know you're here because science and hey
don't do Norman like that now there's an
old saying that guides the work of
fiction writers show don't tell other
words a bad novelist will say he became
anxious and that's just telling but a
good novelist will describe the
character shaking hands and Beads of
sweat and heavy breathing and in that
way the reader forms an idea of anxiety
in their own minds and you need to do
the same thing with cont talization show
don't tell so for this contextualization
paragraph you could show or demonstrate
that social and cultural tension before
1900 by talking about southern
segregation and violence toward black
Americans which led to the Exodusters
migration in the late 19th century or
you could talk about the growth of
industrial capitalism in the Gilded Age
which significantly contributed to
people migrating into cities looking for
work okay so now that you know all that
let me give you a formula for writing
this paragraph the T vocabulary explain
tiing so write two or three sentences
like this name your vocabulary and then
explain explain what it means name your
vocabulary and then explain what it
means name your vocabulary then explain
what it means and then write one more
sentence tying what you just wrote to
the topic of your thesis this sentence
is crucial for earning the point and it
doesn't have to be that complicated for
a Spanish colonization example you just
need to say something like this this
demonstrates that the social structure
of the Americas was fundamentally
different than the structures the
Spanish would bring with them and that's
it so in summary what has Norman taught
us in your contextualization be specific
and make sure it's related to the
category of the problem thanks Norman
now the real question is how are you
supposed to recall all the information
related to the topic of your prompt and
for that you should watch this video
right here where I tell you about how to
study the course thematically and if you
learn what I say there contextualization
will be a brief you can also click here
to check out my AP review packs which
have everything you need to get a five
on your exam I'll catch you on the
flipflop I'm l